Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers, 1900s-1970s (bulk 1914-1937 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. ["Zametki o naturalistakh"]: 3 transcripts of OM's notebook (undated), 1 folder (Folder 5)
  1. 7 sheets in hand of NM -- 2. complete typewritten transcript (order of entries different from transcript 1) -- 3. typewritten transcript (order of entries same as in transcript 2), cut up, fragments in additional envelope
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu: typewritten transcript of OM's notebook; entries transcribed were written for different essays, undated; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu, 1931; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  Author's notebook drafts for essays "Moskva" and "Sevan"; 1 complete notebook, 10 notebook fragments in OM's hand; 1 fragment (2 sheets) of NM's transcript; fragments collated in individual envelopes, description on covers
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. "Vokrug naturalistov": author's final manuscript and drafts; 5 envelopes with collated items (1931), undated; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  1. author's final manuscript: collated fragments on 24 notebook sheets -- 2. OM's draft of sheet 14 -- 3. OM's draft of sheet 18 -- 4. author's final manuscript, collated fragments on 8 notebook sheets -- 5. one draft sheet; fragment of draft for ["Pallas"] on obverse
- Puteshestvie v Armeniiu. Addition to essay "Vokrug naturalistov" published as ["Literaturnyi stil' Darvina"]: manuscripts and drafts; 6 envelopes with collated items (undated), 1 folder (Folder 9)
  1-3. draft of first version (I. Semenko): collated fragments in 3 envelopes, most in hand of OM, some in hand of NM (dictated to her by author) -- 4. draft manuscript: collated fragments on 18 sheets, most in hand of OM, some in hand of NM (dictated to her by author), note by I. Semenko on missing fragments (for their typewritten transcript see Box 5, Fol. 1) -- 5. newspaper version of essay: manuscript in hand of NM -- 6. fragments of intermediate version of article: manuscript in hand of NM (dictated to her by OM)
- 1. Printed fragment of Anthology of Russian Poetry OM was editing (undated). 2. Photocopy of 3 poems: proofreading sheets (1930-1931), 1 folder (Folder 10)
- Original Binders and Folders, undated; 1 box
- 32101037066998 (Box 1)
- 32101037067012 (Box 2)
- 32101037067020 (Box 3)
- 32101037067038 (Box 4)
- 32101037067517 (Box 5)
- 32101037067509 (Box 6)